Preliminary Guide to the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences Records, 1968 - 1991
University Archives Duke University
Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences records 1968 - 1991
Duke University. Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences.
20.0 Linear Feet 19000 Items
University Archives, Duke University
The Duke University Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences (UFCAS), established in 1971, guided undergraduate education in arts and sciences, adopted academic regulations and admissions policies, advised on financial aid and recognized academic achievement. It succeeded the Undergraduate Faculty Council after the body no longer included representatives from the engineering and nursing schools. In 1991, UFCAS voted to disband and reorganize as the Arts and Sciences Council. Records include bylaws, minutes, correspondence, memoranda, rosters, reports, and other records of the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences at Duke University. Most of the records were created by the UFCAS Committees, which included: Curriculum, Courses of Instruction, Honors, Study Abroad, Program II, Academic Standards, Advising, Undergraduate Admissions and Financial Aid, Residential Life, Freshman Year, Advanced Placement, Athletics and Recreation, Health Science Education, and Non-western Studies. Materials range in date from 1968 to 1991.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Unprocessed materials are closed pending processing.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1974-1992.
Historical Note
The Duke University Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences (UFCAS), established in 1971, guided undergraduate education in arts and sciences, adopted academic regulations and admissions policies, advised on financial aid and recognized academic achievement. It succeeded the Undergraduate Faculty Council after the body no longer included representatives from the engineering and nursing schools. Council membership consisted of the president, provost, dean of the undergraduate college, and elected members of the faculties of the humanities, natural sciences, and social sciences. The dean presided at meetings, while a member of the faculty was elected chair of the Executive Committee.
Most of Council's work was done through its standing and ad hoc committees, which included: Curriculum, Courses of Instruction, Honors, Study Abroad, Program II, Academic Standards, Advising, Undergraduate Admissions and Financial Aid, Residential Life, Freshman Year, Advanced Placement, Athletics and Recreation, Health Science Education, and Non-western Studies. In 1991, UFCAS voted to disband and reorganize as the Arts and Sciences Council.
Collection Overview
Records include bylaws, minutes, correspondence, memoranda, rosters, reports, and other records of the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences at Duke University. The Program II files contain some identifiable student records and are regulated by FERPA. The records also contains materials from a prior body, the Undergraduate Faculty Council, which concern ongoing matters.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Duke University -- Administration
Duke University -- Admission
Duke University. Arts and Sciences Council
Duke University -- Curricula
Duke University -- Faculty
Duke University -- Faculty -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.
Duke University. Program II
Duke University -- Students
Duke University. Undergraduate Faculty Council
Duke University. Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences
Education, Higher -- Aims and objectives.
Education, Higher -- Curricula
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Ad Hoc Committee on the Quality of Teaching, 1981-1983 [A85-12] (Box 1-2)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on the Quality of Teaching, Reference Materials (Box 3)
  - Committee on Student Writing [A86-70] (Box 4)
  - Minutes, 1971/72-1978/79 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1979/80-1983/84 (Box 6)
  - Agenda index, 1971-1984
  - Minutes (summary), agendas, rosters, reports (Box 7)
  - Residential Life Committee, 1968-1978 (Box 8-9)
  - Minutes, agenda index, 1984-1991 (Box 10)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on the Curriculum, 1985 [A94-137] (Box 11)
    - Structure and Choice in Liberal Education [A92-7] (Box 12)
    - 1985-1986 [A92-7] (Box 13)
  - Committees: A -- App (Box 14)
  - Committees: Athletics -- Non-western (Box 15)
  - Committees: Study Abroad (Box 16)
  - Bylaws and organization [A98-60]
  - Curriculum Committee, 1971-1979 [A84-93] (Box 17)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1979-1982 [A84-93, A81-55] (Box 18)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1980-1982 [A84-93] (Box 19)
  - Chair records, 1973-1979 [A82-33, A76-203] (Box 20)
  - Chair records, 1973-1984 [A82-33, A76-203, A94-88] (Box 21)
  - Program II, 1968-1975 (Box 22)
    Program II files are restricted: student records.
  - Curriculum Committee Review of the New Curriculum, questionnaires and data, 1974 (Box 23-24)
  - Special Committee of Educational Policy and Programs in Trinity College, Wardropper Committee, 1978-1981 [A80-42, A92-86] (Box 25-26)
  - Committee on Honors, 1961-1977 (Box 27-28)
Related Material
Undergraduate Faculty Council records.
University Archives, Duke University.
Arts and Sciences Council records.
University Archives, Duke University.